<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vinayjain.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://vinayjain.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-23T22:32:34+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Vinay Jain</title><subtitle>Developer / Tinkerer</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tabs in Xcode 12</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/tabs-in-xcode-12" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tabs in Xcode 12" /><published>2021-05-10T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2021-05-10T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/tabs-in-xcode-12</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/tabs-in-xcode-12">&lt;p&gt;Xcode 12 released with a change to file navigation. It is totally different than how it was in earlier versions. Personally, I hate it and I am not sure why was this change made the default navigation style overriding the previous one I preferred. Even after using this editor for 3-4 months, I can’t figure out how to navigate to the right file. Keyboard shortcuts don’t work, the standard macOS gestures to go back and forward don’t work as expected. The only way to reach the desired file I could find was to fallback to the Quick open dialogue(⌘ + ⇧ + O) and it’s super counter-productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/xcode-navigation/tabs.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fix&quot;&gt;The Fix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Xcode 12, files open in two types of tabs, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;window tabs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tabs&lt;/code&gt;, yeah even the names don’t make any sense. Window tabs are the old Xcode 11(and earlier) style tabs and the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tabs&lt;/code&gt; are the new child tabs. If you would like to go back to the old style navigation where the gestures and keyboard shortcuts work, you can do it easily from Xcode preferences. But doing so took me a few hit and trials as the options are not well documented. The solution is to navigate to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferences &amp;gt; Navigation&lt;/code&gt; and change the navigation style to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Open in place&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/xcode-navigation/fix.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This configuration completely hides the child tabs and all the shortcuts and gestures work fine. I also prefer to have the Optional and Double-click navigation to use window tabs as they seem more natural, like how new links/tabs open in a web browser, you can choose what works for you. Most of my friends were facing this issue, if you were also facing this, I hope this post helps you the way it helped me and my friends. ;)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">Xcode 12 released with a change to file navigation. It is totally different than how it was in earlier versions. Personally, I hate it and I am not sure why was this change made the default navigation style overriding the previous one I preferred. Even after using this editor for 3-4 months, I can’t figure out how to navigate to the right file. Keyboard shortcuts don’t work, the standard macOS gestures to go back and forward don’t work as expected. The only way to reach the desired file I could find was to fallback to the Quick open dialogue(⌘ + ⇧ + O) and it’s super counter-productive.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keep Going: Austin Kleon</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/keep-going" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keep Going: Austin Kleon" /><published>2021-04-25T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2021-04-25T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/keep-going</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/keep-going">&lt;p&gt;After Steal Like an Artist and Show Your Work, in Keep Going, Austin Kleon talks about 10 ways to stay creative and focussed in good and bad times. These ideas are written primarily for writers and artists but these can be applied to anyone trying to sustain a meaningful and productive life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the points mentioned in the book are stolen from somewhere else, so you might find some things which you already know and some things which do not apply to you at all. Take what you need and leave the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/everyday.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“None of us know what will happen. Don’t spend time worrying about it. Make the most beautiful thing you can. Try to do that every day. That’s it.”
&lt;cite&gt;- Laurie Anderson&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What would you do if you were stuck in one place, and every day was exactly the same, and nothing that you did mattered?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How you answer this question is your art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is not linear. It’s not a straight line from point A to point B. It’s more like a loop, or a spiral, in which you keep coming back to a new starting point after every project. No matter how successful you get, no matter what level of achievement you reach, you will never really “arrive.” Other than death, there is no finish line or retirement for a person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have so little control over our lives. The only thing we can really control is what we spend our days on. What we work on and how hard we work on it. The best thing you can do if you want to make art is to pretend you’re starring in your own remake of Groundhog Day: Yesterday’s over, tomorrow may never come, there’s just today and what you can do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any man can fight the battles of just one day. It is only when we add the burden of those two awful eternities, yesterday and tomorrow, that we break down. It is not the experience of today that drives men mad, it is the remorse or bitterness for something which happened yesterday or the dread of what tomorrow may bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creative journey is not one in which you’re crowned the triumphant hero and live happily ever after. The real creative journey is one in which you wake up every day with more work to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“How we spend our days is, of course, how we spend our lives.”
&lt;cite&gt;- Annie Dillard&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/establish_routine.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A daily routine will get you through the day and help you make the most of it. When you don’t know what to do next, your routine tells you. When you don’t have much time, a routine helps you make the little time you have count. When you have all the time in the world, a routine helps you make sure you don’t waste it. To establish your own routine, you have to spend some time observing your days and your moods. When your days pretty much have the same shape, the days that don’t have that shape become even more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little imprisonment—if it’s of your own making—can set you free. Rather than restricting your freedom, a routine gives you freedom by protecting you from the ups and downs of life and helping you take advantage of your limited time, energy, and talent. A routine establishes good habits that can lead to your best work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/make_lists.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lists bring order to the chaotic universe. A list gets all your ideas out of your head and clears the mental space so you’re actually able to do something about them. Make a big list of everything that needs to get done, pick the most pressing thing to do, and do it. Each day, just have a starting point and once you have a starting point the work seems to make itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/how_to_be_happy.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there’s something you want to do in the future but don’t have time for right now, add it to a “Someday/Maybe” list. Create a single document–a spark file—every time you have an idea, add it to the file, and then revisit the list every couple of months. Sometimes it’s important to make a list of what you won’t do. Every list should be a collection with purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Your list is your past and your future. Carry at all times. Prioritize: today, this week, and eventually. You will someday die with items still on your list, but for now, while you live, your list helps prioritize what can be done in your limited time.” 
&lt;cite&gt;— Tom Sachs&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every day is going to turn out the way we want it to. The important thing is to make it to the end of the day, no matter what. When the sun goes down and you look back on the day, go easy on yourself. A little self-forgiveness goes a long way. Before you go to bed, make a list of anything you did accomplish, and write down a list of what you want to get done tomorrow. Then forget about it. A day that seems like waste now might turn out to have a purpose or use or beauty to it later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/bliss_station.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disconnect from the world to connect with yourself. You must play a little hide-and-seek in order to produce something worth being found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must have a room, or a certain hour or a day, where you don’t know what was in the newspapers that morning, you don’t know who your friends are, you don’t know what you owe anybody, you don’t know what anybody owes to you. This is a place where you can simply experience and bring forth what you are and what you might be. This is the place of creative incubation. At first you may find that nothing happens there. But if you have a sacred place and use it, something eventually will happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A bliss station can be not just a where, but also a when. Not just a sacred space, but also a sacred time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest need of our time is to clean out the enormous mass of mental and emotional rubbish that clutters our minds and makes of all political and social life a mass illness. Without this housecleaning, we cannot begin to see. Unless we see, we cannot think. Everybody gets so much information all day long that they lose their common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you reach for your phone or your laptop upon waking, you’re immediately inviting anxiety and chaos into your life. You’re also bidding adieu to some of the most potentially fertile moments in the life of a creative person. If you’re using your phone to wake up and it’s ruining your mornings, try this: Before you go to bed, plug your phone into an outlet across the room, or somewhere out of arm’s reach. When you wake up, try your best not to look at it. There are so many better ways to wake up: Head to your bliss station, eat breakfast, stretch, do some exercises, take a walk, run, listen to Mozart, shower, read a book, play with your kids, or just be silent for a bit. Even if it’s for fifteen minutes, give yourself some time in the morning to not be completely horrified by the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The phone gives us a lot but it takes away three key elements of discovery: loneliness, uncertainty, and boredom. Those have always been where creative ideas come from.”
&lt;cite&gt; —Lynda Barry &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/say_no.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect your sacred space and time, you have to learn how to decline all sorts of invitations from the world. You must learn how to say “no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Say not to everyone who is not me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has created a human phenomenon called FOMO: the Fear Of Missing Out. It’s the sense, scrolling through your feeds, that everybody out there is having a much better time than you are. The only antidote is JOMO: the Joy Of Missing Out. Saying “no” to the world can be really hard, but sometimes it’s the only way to say “yes” to your art and your sanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/do_verb.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of people want to be the noun without doing the verb. They want the job title without the work. Let go of the thing that you’re trying to be (the noun), and focus on the actual work you need to be doing (the verb). Doing the verb will take you someplace further and far more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pick the wrong noun to aspire to, you’ll be stuck with the wrong verb, too. If you only aspire to be a “creative,” you might simply spend your time signaling that you are one: wearing designer eyeglasses, typing on your Macbook Pro, and Instagramming photos of yourself in your sun-drenched studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job titles can mess you up. Job titles, if they’re taken too seriously, will make you feel like you need to work in a way that befits the title, not the way that fits the actual work. Job titles can also restrict the kinds of work that you feel like you can do. If you wait for someone to give you a job title before you do the work, you might never get to do the work at all. You can’t wait around for someone to call you an artist before you make art. You’ll never make it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If and when you finally get to be the noun—when that coveted job title is bestowed upon you by others—don’t stop doing your verb. Job titles aren’t really for you, they’re for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/work_play.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve lost your playfulness, practice for practice’s sake. You don’t have to go to such dramatic lengths as combustion. Musicians can jam without making a recording. Writers and artists can type or draw out a page and throw it away. Photographers can take photos and immediately delete them. When nothing’s fun anymore, try to make the worst thing you can. The ugliest drawing. The crummiest poem. The most obnoxious song. Making intentionally bad art is a ton of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You must practice being stupid, dumb, unthinking, empty. Then you will be able to DO . . . Try to do some BAD work—the worst you can think of and see what happens but mainly relax and let everything go to hell—you are not responsible for the world—you are only responsible for your work—so DO IT.”
&lt;cite&gt;- Sol LeWitt&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/make_gifts.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“God walks out of the room when you’re thinking about money.”
&lt;cite&gt; —Quincy Jones &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re now trained to heap praise on our loved ones by using market terminology. The minute anybody shows any talent for anything, we suggest they turn it into a profession. This is our best compliment: telling somebody they’re so good at what they love to do they could make money at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who’s turned their passion into their breadwinning knows this is dangerous territory. One of the easiest ways to hate something you love is to turn it into your job: taking the thing that keeps you alive spiritually and turning it into the thing that keeps you alive literally. You must be mindful of what potential impact monetizing your passions could have on your life. You might find that you’re better off with a day job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Do what you love” + low overhead = a good life.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Do what you love” + “I deserve nice things” = a time bomb.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/ignore_numbers.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digitizing your work and sharing it online means that it is subject to the world of online metrics: website visits, likes, favorites, shares, reblogs, retweets, follower counts, and more. It’s easy to become as obsessed with online metrics as money. It can then be tempting to use those metrics to decide what to work on next, without taking into account how shallow those metrics really are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you share work online, try to ignore the numbers at least every once in a while. Increase the time between your sharing and receiving feedback. Post something and don’t check the response for a week. Turn off the analytics for your blog and write about whatever you want. Download a browser plug-in that makes the numbers disappear from social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Suckcess,” on the other hand, is success on somebody else’s terms. Or undeserved success. Or when something you think sucks becomes successful. Or when success or chasing after it just plain starts to suck. If you’re bummed out and hating your work, pick somebody special in your life and make something for them. If you have a big audience, make them something special and give it away. Or maybe even better: Volunteer your time and teach someone else how to make what you make and do what you do. See how it feels. See whether it puts you in a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/extra_ordinary.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s as true today as it ever was: He who seeks beauty will find it.”
&lt;cite&gt; –Bill Cunnigham &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s impossible to pay proper attention to your life if you are hurtling along at lightning speed. &lt;em&gt;When people look slowly, they make discoveries&lt;/em&gt;. To slow down and pay attention to your world, pick up a pencil and a piece of paper and start drawing what you see. (The pencil’s best feature is that it has no way of interrupting you with texts or notifications.) You might find that this helps you discover the beauty you’ve missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your attention is one of the most valuable things you possess, which is why everyone wants to steal it from you. First you must protect it, and then you must point it in the right direction. What you choose to pay attention to is the stuff your life and work will be made of. We pay attention to the things we really care about, but sometimes what we really care about is hidden from us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has turned us all into politicians. And brands. Everyone’s supposed to be a brand now, and the worst thing in the world is to be off-brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But to be on brand is to be 100 percent certain of who you are and what you do, and certainty, in art and in life, is not only completely overrated, it is also a roadblock to discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/slay_monsters.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might not be meant to be an artist. You might be meant to teach kids math or raise money for a food bank or start a company that makes Rubik’s Cubes for babies. Don’t rule out quitting. There is going to be an insane amount of work ahead, and your time might be spent better elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If making your art is adding net misery to the world, walk away and do something else. Find something else to do with your time, something that makes you and the people around you feel more alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world doesn’t necessarily need more great artists. It needs more decent human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/change_mind.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to hold two opposed ideas in the mind at the same time, and still retain the ability to function. One should, for example, be able to see that things are hopeless and yet be determined to make them otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re afraid of changing our minds because we’re afraid of the consequences of changing our minds. What will people think? Social media has turned us all into politicians. And brands. Everyone’s supposed to be a brand now, and the worst thing in the world is to be off-brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“But to be on brand is to be 100 percent certain of who you are and what you do, and certainty, in art and in life, is not only completely overrated, it is also a roadblock to discovery.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/smart_enough.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, to change your mind is to do some real thinking. Thinking requires an environment in which you can try out all sorts of ideas and not be judged for them. To change your mind, you need a good place to have some bad ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet, unfortunately, is no longer a safe place to do any kind of experimental thinking, particularly for somebody with an audience or any kind of “brand.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re going to change your mind, you might have to go off-brand, and offline is the place to be off-brand. Your bliss station, your studio, a paper journal, a private chat room, a living room full of trusted loved ones: These are the places to really think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Thinking is necessarily, thoroughly, and wonderfully social. Everything you think is a response to what someone else has thought and said.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interacting with people who don’t share our perspective forces us to rethink our ideas, strengthen our ideas, or trade our ideas for better ones. When you’re only interacting with like-minded people all the time, there’s less and less opportunity to be changed. Everybody knows that feeling you get when you’re hanging out with people who love the same art, listen to the same music, and watch the same movies: It’s comforting at first, but it can also become incredibly boring and ultimately stifling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you really want to explore ideas, you should consider hanging out with people who aren’t so much like-minded as like-hearted. These are people who are “temperamentally disposed to openness and have habits of listening.” People who are generous, kind, caring, and thoughtful. People who, when you say something, “think about it, rather than just simply react.” People you feel good around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most everybody alive is so obsessed with what’s new that they all think about the same things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re having trouble finding people to think with, seek out the dead. They have a lot to say and they are excellent listeners. Read old books. If you want a quick way to escape the noise of contemporary life, break out of your like-minded bubble, and do some good thinking, just visit the past for a bit. It’s inexhaustible: Every day, we’re making more and more of it. Human beings have been around for a long time, and almost every problem you have has probably been written about by some other human living hundreds if not thousands of years before you. If you read old books, you get to add all the years the author lived onto your own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/tidy_up.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about planning and preparation: making sure all the ingredients and tools you need are ready before you set to work. It’s hard to work if you can’t find the things you need when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WHEN IN DOUBT, TIDY UP.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that it says “when in doubt,” not “always.” Tidying up is for when you are stalled out or stuck. Tidying up a studio is not life-changing or magical. It’s just a form of productive procrastination. (Avoiding work by doing other work.) The best thing about tidying is that it busies your hands and loosens up your mind so that you either a) get unstuck or solve a new problem in your head, or b) come across something in the mess that leads to new work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tidying in the hope of obtaining perfect order is stressful work. Tidying without worrying too much about the results can be a soothing form of play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/sleep_tidy.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists and philosophers have long wondered about sleep and what it’s for. They’re slowly catching up to what artists have known all along: Sleep is an excellent tool for tidying up your brain. When you sleep, your body literally flushes out the junk in your head. Neuroscientists have explained that cerebrospinal fluid in your brain starts flowing more rapidly when you sleep, clearing out the toxins and bad proteins that build up in your brain cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/demons.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking is good for physical, spiritual, and mental health. No matter what time you get out of bed, go for a walk. The demons hate it when you get out of bed. Demons hate fresh air. Walking is great for releasing inner demons, but maybe even more important, walking is great for battling our outer demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people who want to control us through fear and misinformation—the corporations, marketers, politicians—want us to be plugged into our phones or watching TV, because then they can sell us their vision of the world. If we do not get outside, if we do not take a walk out in the fresh air, we do not see our everyday world for what it really is, and we have no vision of our own with which to combat disinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we’re glued to our screens, the world looks unreal. Terrible. Not worth saving or even spending time with. Everyone on earth seems like a troll or a maniac or worse. But you get outside and you start walking and you come to your senses. Outside as well, there are a few maniacs and some ugliness, but there are also people smiling, birds chirping, clouds flying overhead…all that stuff. There’s possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So get outside every day. Take long walks by yourself. Take walks with a friend or a loved one or a dog. Walk with a coworker on your lunch break. Grab a plastic bag and a stick and take a litter-picking walk like David Sedaris. Always keep a notebook or camera in your pocket for when you want to stop to capture a thought or an image. Explore the world on foot. See your neighborhood. Meet your neighbors. Talk to strangers. The demons hate fresh air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/garden.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/seasons.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sometimes the harshest winters yielded the most glorious springs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lives, too, have different seasons. Some of us blossom at a young age; others don’t blossom until old age. Our culture mostly celebrates early successes, the people who bloom fast. But those people often wither as quickly as they bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the work is to know which season you’re in, and act accordingly. You have to pay attention to the rhythms and cycles of your creative output and learn to be patient in the off-seasons. You have to give yourself time to change and observe your own patterns. Imitate the trees. Learn to lose in order to recover, and remember that nothing stays the same for long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to know how a thirty-year-old became rich and famous; I want to hear how an eighty-year-old spent her life in obscurity, kept making art, and lived a happy life. These are the people I look to for inspiration. The people who found the thing that made them feel alive and who kept themselves alive by doing it. The people who planted their seeds, tended to themselves, and grew into something lasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;/images/booksummary/keep_going/pass.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outer demons as mentioned in the last chapter—the men who are hell-bent on wrecking this planet, carving it up for profit—they’re not going to last forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day is a potential seed that we can grow into something beautiful. There’s no time for despair. The thing to rejoice in is the fact that one had the good fortune to be born, the odds against being born are astronomical. None of us know how many days we’ll have, so it’d be a shame to waste the ones we get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever life gets overwhelming, go back to chapter one of this book and think about your days. Try your best to fill them in ways that get you a little closer to where you want to be. Go easy on yourself and take your time. Worry less about getting things done. Worry more about things worth doing. Worry less about being a great artist. Worry more about being a good human being who makes art. Worry less about making a mark. Worry more about leaving things better than you found them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep doing your verbs, whatever they may be. Keep going.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book summary" /><summary type="html">After Steal Like an Artist and Show Your Work, in Keep Going, Austin Kleon talks about 10 ways to stay creative and focussed in good and bad times. These ideas are written primarily for writers and artists but these can be applied to anyone trying to sustain a meaningful and productive life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Regex: Pipe operator to find alternatives</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/pipes-in-regular-expressions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regex: Pipe operator to find alternatives" /><published>2021-01-11T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-11T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/pipes-in-regular-expressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/pipes-in-regular-expressions">&lt;p&gt;Regular expressions are probably one of the most under-pursued yet powerful and useful Computer Science skills. As a programmer, in common day-to-day tasks like text–search, replace and input validation I find regular expression to be very efficient. Almost all modern languages and operating systems support text processing with regex and having them in my toolbox makes my workflow more productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, for a side-project I wanted to validate an IP address(IPv4) input by the user. I decided to validate it with regular expressions and quickly came up with a basic pattern for the happy flow–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;^[&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;]{&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;}\.[&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;]{&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;}\.[&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;]{&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;}\.[&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;]{&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;}$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see this expression gives false positives for invalid IP addresses like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;999.999.999.999&lt;/code&gt;. Looks like validating an IP address with a regular expression isn’t as easy as expected. Let’s break it down into smaller sub-problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To write the correct pattern we first need to list down all the valid cases for an IP address. All IPv4 addresses are divided into 4 groups separated with three dots and each of these groups follow the same rules. For an IP address to qualify as validated, each group should be validated by a pattern which considers the following cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/ip-validation-rules.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this picture it is clear that we need to put some kind of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if–else&lt;/code&gt; logic to validate our input. In a programming language this is a trivial task, split the input by dots and validate each group with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if–else&lt;/code&gt; condtions. But I decided to stick with the regular expression approach and continue writing the match pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pipe-operator&quot;&gt;Pipe Operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pipe operator in a regular expression has the same behaviour as in programming languages, it does the logical OR of the operands and returns any of the matching strings. Have a look at the example below to understand it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; pattern = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;(desk|lap)tops&quot;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; regex = &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Regex&lt;/span&gt;(with: pattern)

&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; inputString = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;desktops and laptops and not palmtops&quot;&lt;/span&gt;

regex.&lt;span class=&quot;call&quot;&gt;findMatch&lt;/span&gt;(inputString)

&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// Returns: desktops, laptops&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For IP addresses, in a group, we have to either match one digit, two digits or three digits and additionally cover all the valid cases mentioned in the figure above. And then repeat it four times to validate the entire input. For one group the regex pattern looks like the one shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/one-group-regex.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, if you are thinking this is long just remember that its just for one single group, copy-paste it three more times and check the length. In situations like these when a pattern is repeating we can tell regex to match exactly a particular number of occurences with the help of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt;. Lets assume that we call the group pattern as shown above as “part”. Our final regex will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/complete-regex.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In code, by making the “part” as a variable, the pattern can look exactly like the one shown in figure, let’s see how it looks in Swift:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt; isValidIPAddress(&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt; ip: &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;) -&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Bool&lt;/span&gt; {
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; part = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;[0-9]|[1-9][0-9]|1[0-9][0-9]|2[0-4][0-9]|25[0-5]&quot;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; pattern = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;^&lt;/span&gt;\(part)&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;\\.{3}&lt;/span&gt;\(part)&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;$&quot;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; ip.&lt;span class=&quot;call&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;(of: pattern, options: .&lt;span class=&quot;dotAccess&quot;&gt;regularExpression&lt;/span&gt;) != &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we had chosen to match each group with conditional statements we would’ve filled our code with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if–else&lt;/code&gt; blocks and that would have increased the size of this function by about 4–5 times. With regular expressions our code looks short and clean. Though at first the long patterns make it a little difficult to understand but as you get to know more about regex these patterns start to make a lot of sense. This is one of the many great super powers of regex and like most of the skills in Computer Science, though they are not mandatory but using them will definitely give you a step-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, please let me know if you have any feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech" /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html">Regular expressions are probably one of the most under-pursued yet powerful and useful Computer Science skills. As a programmer, in common day-to-day tasks like text–search, replace and input validation I find regular expression to be very efficient. Almost all modern languages and operating systems support text processing with regex and having them in my toolbox makes my workflow more productive.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setup Plex on Android with LinuxDeploy</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/plex-setup-android" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setup Plex on Android with LinuxDeploy" /><published>2021-01-06T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-06T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/plex-setup-android</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/plex-setup-android">&lt;p&gt;In one of my previous posts, I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;https://vinayjain.me/posts/linux-on-android&quot;&gt;Running Ubuntu/Linux on Android&lt;/a&gt; and there I had mentioned about setting up a media center with Plex. I assumed it to be a straight-forward process but it took me a lot of time to set it up correctly. Though, the final steps here are quick and easy to use, it took a lot of work to come to these steps. The following steps didn’t work for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installing using Plex apt repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manually installing with the deb package from the Plex Download Page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trying all configurations available on the Internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can try other configurations, I am mentioning versions that worked for me. But because of the fragile nature of this setup, other configurations might not work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xiaomi Redmi Note 5 Pro running Android 10, rooted with Magisk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LinuxDeploy 2.6.0-258&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Debian &amp;gt; arm64 &amp;gt; buster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setup-plex&quot;&gt;Setup Plex&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -O https://downloads.plex.tv/plex-media-server-new/1.21.1.3876-3c3adfcb4/debian/plexmediaserver_1.21.1.3876-3c3adfcb4_arm64.deb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extract the deb package in a directory accessible with your current user&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dpkg-deb --extract plexmediaserver_1.21.1.3876-3c3adfcb4_arm64.deb /home/android/plex
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plex&lt;/code&gt; should contain &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;etc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;usr&lt;/code&gt; sub-directories. We need to edit the following files&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;plexmediaserverservice&quot;&gt;plexmediaserver.service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo vim plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/lib/plexmediaserver.service
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
.
.

## ----- Change these two paths to point to the directory in the home folder ----- 

# Environment=&quot;PLEX_MEDIA_SERVER_APPLICATION_SUPPORT_DIR=/var/lib/plexmediaserver/Library/Application Support&quot;
# Environment=PLEX_MEDIA_SERVER_HOME=/usr/lib/plexmediaserver
Environment=&quot;PLEX_MEDIA_SERVER_APPLICATION_SUPPORT_DIR=/home/android/plex/var/lib/plexmediaserver/Library/Application Support&quot;
Environment=PLEX_MEDIA_SERVER_HOME=/home/android/plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver

## ----- Change these two paths to point to the directory in the home folder ----- 

# export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/lib; \
# exec &quot;/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/Plex Media Server&quot;&apos;
export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/home/android/plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/lib; \
exec &quot;/home/android/plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/Plex Media Server&quot;&apos;

Type=simple


## ----- Change the user and group to your user and group ----- 

# User=plex
# Group=plex
User=android
Group=android
.
.
.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;plexmediaserverinit&quot;&gt;plexmediaserver.init&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo vim plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/lib/plexmediaserver.init
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
## ----- Change the user and group to your user and group ----- 
# PlexUser=&quot;plex&quot;
PlexUser=&quot;android&quot;


## ----- Change these two paths to point to the directory in the home folder ----- 

# PlexHome=&quot;/usr/lib/plexmediaserver&quot;
# PlexAppSuppDir=&quot;/var/lib/plexmediaserver/Library/Application Support&quot;
PlexHome=&quot;/home/android/plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver&quot;
PlexAppSuppDir=&quot;/home/android/plex/var/lib/plexmediaserver/Library/Application Support&quot;


PlexTempDir=&quot;/tmp&quot;
PlexStackSize=3000

.
.
.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all the necessary configiration needed. Plex server can be started by running the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plexmediaserver.init&lt;/code&gt; service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo ./home/android/plex/usr/lib/plexmediaserver/lib/plexmediaserver.init start
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default Plex media server runs on the port &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;32400&lt;/code&gt;, to configure Plex and add media to it, access the dashboard using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://&amp;lt;your-server-ip&amp;gt;:32400&lt;/code&gt; in a web browser. You’ll be welcomed with a configuration screen from where you can login to your Plex account and add photos, movies, tv shows etc to serve from your Android Phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know if you face any problems or find another way of setting up Plex easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vinayjain.me/posts/linux-on-android&quot;&gt;Running Ubuntu/Linux on Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pimylifeup.com/raspberry-pi-plex-server/&quot;&gt;Install Plex with apt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plex.tv/media-server-downloads/#plex-media-server&quot;&gt;Plex Server Downloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://magiskmanager.com/&quot;&gt;Magisk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/meefik/linuxdeploy&quot;&gt;LinuxDeploy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">In one of my previous posts, I talked about Running Ubuntu/Linux on Android and there I had mentioned about setting up a media center with Plex. I assumed it to be a straight-forward process but it took me a lot of time to set it up correctly. Though, the final steps here are quick and easy to use, it took a lot of work to come to these steps. The following steps didn’t work for me:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remote Configurations &amp;amp; AB Tests</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/feature-toggle-service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remote Configurations &amp;amp; AB Tests" /><published>2020-12-22T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-22T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/feature-toggle-service</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/feature-toggle-service">&lt;p&gt;Recently, during a video conference call I was asked to tap on a button not available on the app I was using. Then I was asked to update the app from the App store and I confirmed that I had the latest version available. I told them that it’s probably an AB test. Turns out, it was an alien term for most of the attendees from a non-tech background. Appreciating their curiosity I took the next few minutes to explain them what it meant. Being constrained with the time and audience I didn’t explain it completely and got away by saying that it needs a separate discussion to get into the details. Probably, a blogpost is a good idea to reach a bigger audience, I’ll try to keep it as non-tech as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-an-ab-test-anyway&quot;&gt;What is an AB test anyway?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you and I started an icecream parlour. Unfortunately, our business is not doing well and we decide to add a new Chocolate flavor in our offerings. You like the Belgian Chocolate icecream and believe that the customers will love it too. Me on the other hand thinks that the American Chocolate will sell more. Because we are low on funds we don’t want to place a bulk order for any of these chocolates and end up making a loss. Instead, we decide to buy small amounts of both &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;merican and &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;elgian chocolates to run an experiment of selling both icecreams for 7-days. Based on the results of this experiment we’ll get to know the chocolate flavor our customers prefer and eventually we’ll place bulk order for that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experiment which helps us to determine the preferred chocolate flavor of our customers is an example of AB tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;AB testing is a process of simultaneouly experimenting two variants of a product against a metric that defines success to determine which variation to use in the real-world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar conflicts arise in the software development process, let me walk you through a normal feature development process in a product company and how it reaches you from the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feature-development&quot;&gt;Feature Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Product managers thinks of building a new feature or an improvement to an existing feature; goes to the designer gets a prototype ready shows it to the client and the client proposes a different solution or completely rejects it saying it won’t work. This is a classic problem of &lt;strong&gt;HIPPO&lt;/strong&gt;(HIghest Paid Persons Opinion) and the only way to avoid this is with AB tests, because data speaks for itself. This data can only be collected when the variation for the existing feature is developed, manager gets approval to build the proposed feature and gathers a team of rockstar developers to work on it. The developers work on the new feature keping the AB testability in mind and make it ready to deploy on production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feature-deployment&quot;&gt;Feature Deployment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Releasing the feature can be as simple as clicking a button but if your product is an app distributed from an app store then you can also use &lt;strong&gt;Phase Release&lt;/strong&gt; utility provided by most of the stores. With this utility you can set what percent of users should get this update, if you set a value of “5” then app store will release it to only 5 in every 100 users of the app. You can treat it as a safety net for your app, if anything blows up in production it will affect only 5% users the rest of the 95% won’t even realise. Please note that this only works for users who have auto-update enabled, if any user goes and downloads the app from the store directly there’s no one stopping them to get the latest app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phased releases are not limited to apps, the technical term for it is Canary Release and it can be used for anything that can be released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the app with the new “Feature” has reached our users, how does it decide which variant to show?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-finally-ab-test&quot;&gt;We finally AB test!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A software is dumb and does whatever its instructed to do. The developers build the feature in an AB testable way so they put the necessary code to toggle this feature for certain users matching a criteria. A match is validated usually with the help of a service like Firebase Remote Config or an in-house Feature Configuration service. An AB testable code can be something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; isNewFeatureEnabled = &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;ConfigurationService&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;property&quot;&gt;shared&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;call&quot;&gt;getConfig&lt;/span&gt;(for: &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;NEW_FEATURE_ENABLED&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)

&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; isNewFeatureEnabled {
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;call&quot;&gt;performNewFeatureActions&lt;/span&gt;()
} &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; {
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;call&quot;&gt;performOldFeatureActions&lt;/span&gt;()
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ConfigurationService&lt;/code&gt; relies on the analytics data(more on this below) you share with the app. Behind the scenes, this service pre-computes a list of users who satisfy the match criteria and the code above just checks the presence of this user on that list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;analytics-data&quot;&gt;Analytics Data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the apps that we use track our activity in some way. In addition to the device specific details like operating system, device type, geo-location; information is also shared in the form of events like opening a screen, tapping a button, adding money to the digital wallet, liking a picture, opening and watching a video, sending a message etc. Simply put, whatever you do inside an app the developer knows because you quickly “Agree” the Terms and Conditions of using the app. Again, there are services available in the market which helps you track the user activity; Mixpanel, CleverTap, Firebase, Google Analytics are the one’s that I have used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of this data the product team can create user buckets to be consumed by the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ConfigurationService&lt;/code&gt;. These buckets can include users in particular geography, total amount spent, users who liked a picture or watched a particular video etcs. This way your own behavior on the app determines what you see on the app and offcourse, it can be different for two different users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-the-feature-performance&quot;&gt;Measuring the Feature Performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analytics data that has been shared with the app contains information about the newly added “Feature” also. Looking at this data, product managers and data analysts/scientists perform some magical calculations and judge the behavior of the user with respect to this feature and check the results against the metric that defines success. If the results are good and everything works as expected the feature can be released to more users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the new change is not performing upto the expectations, managers look at user drop-points and think of a strategy to avoid the drop-point or make it easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the AB test is complete and the changes are permanent, it is the developers responsibility to cleanup the toggles in the next releases. It should be removed from the code and the configuration system to improve the maintainability of the codebase. Some services like LaunchDarkly periodically reminds you to review the toggles and cleanup that are not being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth mentioning that AB testing is not just for measuring performance of new features(the icecreams example), it can be used to measure the performance of a change(like UX improvements) compared to the existing implementation. Infact, in the real-world AB testing is used more for the latter case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alternatives-for-b2b-products&quot;&gt;Alternatives for B2B products?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AB testing makes a lot of sense for B2C products where the business can exploit the user provided data to make decisions. But with B2B products where enough data points cannot be provided, using an AB test doesn’t help much and in that case we rely on the feedback of super users and additional alpha/beta users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though, I explained everything here in the context of feature development, a ConfigurationService and phased releases are not limited to this only. Product teams use it for use-cases like reducing risk, load testing, easy rollbacks etc. These are amazing tools and using them properly can help in improving the user experience and also in growing the business. Based on your business use-cases you can identify how AB testing can help you with the growth of your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would highly appreciate your feedback and questions on this. Please let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://exp-platform.com/hippo/&quot;&gt;HIPPO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CanaryRelease.html&quot;&gt;Canary Release - Martin Fowler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/docs/remote-config&quot;&gt;Firebase Remote Config&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clevertap.com/&quot;&gt;CleverTap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mixpanel.com/&quot;&gt;Mixpanel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://launchdarkly.com/blog/launched-ready-to-remove-notifications-in-slack/&quot;&gt;LaunchDarkly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">Recently, during a video conference call I was asked to tap on a button not available on the app I was using. Then I was asked to update the app from the App store and I confirmed that I had the latest version available. I told them that it’s probably an AB test. Turns out, it was an alien term for most of the attendees from a non-tech background. Appreciating their curiosity I took the next few minutes to explain them what it meant. Being constrained with the time and audience I didn’t explain it completely and got away by saying that it needs a separate discussion to get into the details. Probably, a blogpost is a good idea to reach a bigger audience, I’ll try to keep it as non-tech as possible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Google Photos</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/google-photos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Google Photos" /><published>2020-11-18T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2020-11-18T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/google-photos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/google-photos">&lt;p&gt;Google Photos was launched in May 2015 with a motive to retire Google+ Photos and with a promise to give unlimited storage for photos upto 16 Megapixel and videos upto a 1080p resolution. I take photos from my iPhone, it limits the photo quality to 12MP which means, full resolution photos from my phone will get free cloud storage forever. And like all other Google products, they did mention that they’ll be using my photos to improve their AI for face-recognition and search. As long as my ugly pictures weren’t made public, I am fine with that. Along with me, by May 2017, half a billion users joined the bandwagon and got addicted. With their powerful AI, Google Photos easily solved a great problem of arranging, filtering and searching the photos and now its impossible to get away from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Storing the pictures was never a problem. It was to make sense of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google recently announced an update in their storage policy stating &lt;em&gt;Starting June 1, 2021, any new photos and videos you upload will count toward the free 15 GB of storage that comes with every Google Account or the additional storage you’ve purchased as a Google One member.&lt;/em&gt; And with this our beloved service is no longer free. Like everyone else, I was disappointed. Not because I am a non-paying user and have to pay now but because they initially promised it to be free and are now asking me to pay for it. This seems like betrayal. A comment from a friend sums it up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was already paying for it. But now I am less pissed at Apple not giving free storage for photos.
&lt;cite&gt;- Jagrat Desai&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a software engineer, I respect the work of other developers and pay for many services and subscriptions on the internet. But will I pay for the Google One subscription? First, let’s see if a service like this is worth paying for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On their blog, Google also mentioned that &lt;em&gt;more than 4 trillion photos are stored in Google Photos, and every week 28 billion new photos and videos are uploaded&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-box&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;321px&quot; height=&quot;262px&quot; src=&quot;/images/apple-iphone-se-pic.svg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;image-box-item&quot; width=&quot;321px&quot; height=&quot;262px&quot; src=&quot;/images/apple-iphone-se-pic-live.svg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 12MP photo clicked on my phone takes up 2MB of storage space and I have Live Photos enabled which takes upto 7MB. Nowadays, almost everyone has a smartphone with a great camera which captures a high resolution image. Let’s assume, on an average every new photo uploaded on Google Photos from today will take 3MB of storage space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The estimated storage needed for 28 billion new photos uploaded every week will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weekly&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Monthly(4 weeks)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Yearly(52 weeks)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;28 billion * 3MB ≅ 84,000TB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4 * 84,000TB ≅ 336,000TB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;52 * 84,000TB ≅ 4,368,000TB&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lets assume on an average each of the previous 4 trillion photos takes 1MB of storage space on the disk. The total disk space used is approximately&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4 trillion * 1MB ≅ 4,000,000TB&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And considering an organisation like Google where uptime and availability of resources is promised, this data must be replicated at least once so just double the calculations. This is a massive amount of storage space and we haven’t considered videos yet. Imagine running a marathan, 42kms, yes thats the distance you’ll have to run if you put &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;4,000,000&lt;/code&gt; HDDs with 1TB capacity in a row. Extreme computing power is needed just to keep a service running at this scale and storage is probably one of the cheapest part of it, don’t get me started on the cost of high performance CPUs and GPUs driving that amazing AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;now-that-we-know-what-google-photos-is-should-you-and-i-pay-for-it&quot;&gt;Now that we know what Google Photos is, should you and I pay for it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the calculations above, its clear that a service like this isn’t cheap and if a giant like Google had to change their pricing strategy then I don’t think any other company can afford to give it away for free. With similar examples like YouTube, Medium, Amazon it is evident that the free services are going away or getting worse in experience. Photos are important for a lot of people and for them it totally makes sense to pay for it. I am just a casual photographer but I do have about 150GB photos+videos stored there. Even if I think about migrating to any other service, the effort of downloading and reuploading this data isn’t worth it. However, the fact that Google does all the magic on their servers by using my data concerns me. I let them use my data because in turn they let me use their storage space. &lt;em&gt;Seems like a valid transaction&lt;/em&gt;. But now they are asking for an additional input from my side and the transaction &lt;em&gt;doesn’t seem valid anymore&lt;/em&gt;. If I pay they’ll offer me additional tech support, I don’t need their tech support I know tech and I figure out most of the issues on my own, so no thanks! Unless they have additional things to offer me and validate the transaction I would avoid paying for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paying-for-icloud-makes-more-sense&quot;&gt;Paying for iCloud makes more sense?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed! Apple respects user’s privacy, its the foundation of all their offerings. In contrast to Google Photos, Apple does the magical computation by running those machine learning algorithms on the device itself. Your data is private and no one can look into it. I get the added advantage of the beautiful Photos app on macOS. The transaction also seems valid because its give and take, unlike give(x2) and take. For now, I have stopped the automatic backup from my phone and I’ll probably keep the existing photos on Google and migrate some of them to iCloud over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people might want to self host their data and avoid using all the cloud providers. If you are going to do so, there are amazing free tools like Plex and PhotoView that can help you get most of what Apple and Google offer. But setting up and maintaining a server of this kind will have its own implications. I’ll leave that upto you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Photos&quot;&gt;Google Photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blog.google/products/photos/storage-changes/&quot;&gt;Updating Google Photos’ storage policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://one.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/in/apple-one/&quot;&gt;Apple One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plex.tv/your-media/photos-videos/&quot;&gt;Plex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrisbanes/PhotoView&quot;&gt;PhotoView&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts" /><summary type="html">Google Photos was launched in May 2015 with a motive to retire Google+ Photos and with a promise to give unlimited storage for photos upto 16 Megapixel and videos upto a 1080p resolution. I take photos from my iPhone, it limits the photo quality to 12MP which means, full resolution photos from my phone will get free cloud storage forever. And like all other Google products, they did mention that they’ll be using my photos to improve their AI for face-recognition and search. As long as my ugly pictures weren’t made public, I am fine with that. Along with me, by May 2017, half a billion users joined the bandwagon and got addicted. With their powerful AI, Google Photos easily solved a great problem of arranging, filtering and searching the photos and now its impossible to get away from it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Univeral Pasteboard iOS, macOS, Android</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/shared-pasteboard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Univeral Pasteboard iOS, macOS, Android" /><published>2020-10-03T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2020-10-03T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/shared-pasteboard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/shared-pasteboard">&lt;p&gt;Do you recall the times when you had to touch-type a long website address on your phone’s baby keyboard and wished to copy it from your computer and continue browsing just by pasting the URL in the address bar? Such a painful and frustrating user-experience. I’ve been doing this for a long time, some people might still be doing this but things have changed on the iOS/macOS side and partially on the Android side and the number of WTFs/day have drastically reduced. With some coding, I can further reduce them down, let’s see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple knew this was a problem so they fixed it with Handoff &amp;amp; Continuity. The iPhone and the Mac are my primary devices but I also like using my Android phone, it has a long list of benefits. I am frequently switching devices for their specific features and use-cases, for all the software tinkering I pick my Android device, for example, I am running a &lt;a href=&quot;https://vinayjain.me/posts/linux-on-android&quot;&gt;Linux image on my Android&lt;/a&gt; phone and on top of it I have setup pi-hole and this pi-hole server is set up as a proxy on my router to block ads and social media trackers on all devices in my home network. This hacking can’t be done on iOS because of the securely closed system. I miss some features of the Apple ecosystem when I am on Android, one such feature is Handoff and Continuity. More specifically, the universal pasteboard, the functionality of copying something on one device and pasting on another, really cool! This seems like a very small feature and indeed it is, but its impact on the user experience is huge. My life will be simpler if I can share pasteboard across all my devices including Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/WeekendProject?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#WeekendProject&lt;/a&gt; One of the many advantages of being in the Apple ecosystem is Handoff between apps specifically the shared pasteboard. It&amp;#39;ll be great if it can be shared with Android as well.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vinay Jain (@vinayjn7) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vinayjn7/status/1271058739131330561?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 11, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-build-this&quot;&gt;Lets build this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This implementation triggered as an idea in the evening and I rushed to Twitter to post it for validation. From the top it looks like a really complex system to build, and if I go on to implement the full functionality of Handoff and Continuity, it is indeed a difficult software to build. But when given a thought, what I need is a small subset of Apple’s implementation, the universal pasteboard. To build it, I need to know how Apple did it and what is the tech behind. With some little research, I got to know about BluetoothLE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bluetoothle&quot;&gt;BluetoothLE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handoff &amp;amp; Continuity uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bluetooth.com&quot;&gt;BluetoothLE&lt;/a&gt; (bluetooth low energy), a technology that helps nearby devices to communicate using significantly small data packets and low energy. The Bluetooth specification prefers to call the communicating devices as the Central and the Peripheral but in general terms its a client-server communication. The peripheral advertises one or more services &amp;amp; characteristics, which can be found by the centrals with a Bluetooth scan. A central connects to a peripheral with a pairing process which may or may not require authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The serivces and characteristics are important to understand because that is the only way the central can find a peripheral and send data to it. The central will write data on the characteristics which were advertised by the peripherals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gatt-server&quot;&gt;The GATT server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisement of a service is totally different from data transfer. After pairing, the central is authorised to send data to the peripheral without permission. As the central is writing data to a characteristic, the peripheral needs to know how to handle this data. This can be done by setting up a GATT server on the peripheral. The server knows who is writing data on a particular characteristic and exposes certain methods to handle this data transfer. Our shared pasteboard implementaton relies on the GATT server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;practicality&quot;&gt;Practicality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this case, I am interested in getting pasteboard data from Mac to Android. I want my Android device to be discovered by a nearby Mac, you might think that turning on Bluetooth and pairing Android &amp;amp; Mac would do that. Not completely, because Android is advertising the services it supports like file sharing, Bluetooth tethering etc. Luckily, I can use the standard Bluetooth pairing process of Android and don’t have to write any code for the authentication flow. By the time of writing this post, I couldn’t find any advertised services/characteristics that could potentially link to the Android pasteboard. Unfortunately/fortunately, I had to write all the code for advertisement, services and characteristics, GATT server and for the system pasteboard manipulation. This was just the part on Android side, I still need to write code that will send data to Android. Right! the central code on Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pasteboard-events&quot;&gt;Pasteboard Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anytime I hit Cmd+C on the Mac I need to send the selected data to Android. I initially thought that there must be an event(NSNotification) fired as soon as the pasteboard contents are updated, unfortunately this isn’t the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In computer science there are two ways to get updates from a system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You(subscriber) subscribe to the updates on a system(publisher), and get notified for each change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You keep polling a system on regular time intervals and compare its latest value with the value you currently have. If it doesn’t match that means the system has a new value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, I won’t be able to use the publisher-subscriber model(the optimal approach) here, I had to turn my head towards polling. And like most of times I was able to find a solution with a little help from GitHub, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/Daemon-Devarshi/13efd24f027a775ee862&quot;&gt;Daemon-Devarshi&lt;/a&gt; for their clean Swift implementation. Polling the pasteboard works because the amount of data transferred in polling isn’t that much and I can just ignore the battery related issues for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-central&quot;&gt;The Central&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I already have the pasteboard updates, writing rest of the central code is relatively easy. Apart from the pasteboard code, the central has the following responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep running in background&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connect to the Android phone when pasteboard changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send data to the connected Android phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some help from &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/documentation/corebluetooth&quot;&gt;Core Bluetooth&lt;/a&gt;, it took me a little time to write a macOS script that does all that. Just because I did the custom implementation of services and characteristics the central’s code can further be optimised to scan only for the specific services and characteristics I need. And with this it’s done, I have a working solution for a shared pasteboard between all my devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll probably be pushing all this code on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/vinayjn&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; after I refactor and clean it but I am not sure when. If you are still interested in looking into it let me know and I’ll speed up the process or may be send it to you directly over email.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="hacking" /><summary type="html">Do you recall the times when you had to touch-type a long website address on your phone’s baby keyboard and wished to copy it from your computer and continue browsing just by pasting the URL in the address bar? Such a painful and frustrating user-experience. I’ve been doing this for a long time, some people might still be doing this but things have changed on the iOS/macOS side and partially on the Android side and the number of WTFs/day have drastically reduced. With some coding, I can further reduce them down, let’s see.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Running Ubuntu/Linux on Android</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/linux-on-android" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Running Ubuntu/Linux on Android" /><published>2020-06-17T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-17T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/linux-on-android</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/linux-on-android">&lt;p&gt;Phones have become very powerful these days. Its easy to find an Android phone under $200 that is capable of powering up a desktop computer with decent performance. I was thinking about setting up a media server in my home network so I can watch movies and TV shows on all devices, I was convinced to use a Raspberry Pie for this but then I thought what if I use my Android phone for the same, its much more capable than a pie and has a lot hardware capabilities that the pie doesn’t offer out of the box. So I set course and took out my old Android phone, did some hacking and got the media server working on it. Its a long process to setup the media server and the first step in getting their is to install Ubuntu or any other Linux distribution on the Android phone. I’ll talk about the media server setup some other day but lets see how to install Ubuntu on Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;getting-the-device-ready&quot;&gt;Getting the device ready&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the people I know have at least one abandoned Android phone. Though its completely fine to do, I don’t recommend using your primary phone to follow this post as it would end your phone’s warranty. If you are willing to take the risk you can still follow. First, make sure you have the following items checked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A phone running Android 7+ with root access&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic knowledge of Linux and ssh&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Internet connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tested this approach on the following configurations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xiaomi Redmi Note 5 Pro, running Lineage OS 17.1(Android 10), Qualcomm SDM636 Snapdragon 636 arm64 processor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xiaomi Redmi 1s, running Lineage OS 14.1(Android 7.1.2) Qualcomm MSM8228 Snapdragon 400 ARM processor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;configuration&quot;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux Deploy is an app that makes this process easy, go ahead and install the app from &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ru.meefik.linuxdeploy&quot;&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/a&gt;. You will need root access enabled on your device to get it working. The app greets you with a screen like in the screenshot below, please not that I am currently using version 2.6.0 it might differ if you use another app version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instructions are pretty straight-forward and needs no explanation. Tap on the little settings button at the bottom right and you’ll see a screen as shown below, you can follow the configuration you see here or you can change according to your preference. One important thing to choose is the architecture, in the screenshot you see &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;arm64&lt;/code&gt; which is same as the android phone’s CPU architecture. Its fine to use other architectures as well but I recommend choosing the one which is most compatible with the software you are going to install in the future. The media server I wanted to install works well with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;arm64&lt;/code&gt;. Also, if you don’t know the CPU architecture of your phone you can install CPU-Z from the play store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More about configuration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Image Size - Consider this as the partition size for your Linux installation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Username &amp;amp; Password - Use anything, we will use it to login with ssh&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Privileged Users - Additional custom permissions for the user&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mount points - Use it to mount your internal or external sdcard to use in Ubuntu, more on this later&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SSH - Enable this, we want to access this system inside our home network with ssh.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio - We don’t need it for our usecase&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GUI - Since most of the time we will be accessing it through SSH I have skipped the GUI part. If you need GUI then you can setup a VNC viewer and configure it easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all the configuration that we need for now. Tap on the three dots on the top right and select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Install&lt;/code&gt;, the app will be downloading the entire linux image based on our configuration. Depending on your internet speed, if everything went well, you should see a screen as shown below. Now tap on the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Start&lt;/code&gt; button on the bottom left. The app will validate the configuration and start all the services of the Linux distribution. The result is a fully functional linux operating system just like we have on a desktop computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_7.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we can access this system using ssh. The IP is shown at the top, for me its &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;192.168.0.137&lt;/code&gt;, it might be different for you. From a computer in the same network, you can use the below commands in any shell to login and when it asks for the password just use the password you entered during the configuration, if you forgot your password you can get it by tapping on the settings button on the bottom right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// if your user name is android and IP is 192.168.0.137, use:&lt;/span&gt;
ssh android@192.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;168.0.137&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// Type yes when it asks you to continue connecting to the host
// and enter your password when it asks for it&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are now logged-in to the system and can perform any operations as you want. If you want to avoid entering your password when you login, you can put the public ssh key of your computer in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.ssh/authorized_keys&lt;/code&gt; file. If its not there you’ll have to create it, you can easily find articles on the web if you don’t know how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_8.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mounting-internal-and-external-sdcard&quot;&gt;Mounting internal and external sdcard&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not able to access the phone’s internal storage in the linux file system you will have to map the mount path of the storage in Android file system to a mount point in linux file system. To do this you have to find where is the sdcard mounted in the Android, there are two ways, one with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; and other by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;installing any file manager app&lt;/code&gt;. I am going to tell you the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; way because I don’t want to install any other app for a small usecase. Connect your phone to your computer, make sure USB debugging is enabled, from the terminal execute the following commands&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;➜  ~ adb devices
&lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt; of devices attached
f4936abb	device

➜  ~ adb shell
whyred:/ $ df
&lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Filesystem&lt;/span&gt;               1K-blocks    &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Used Available Use&lt;/span&gt;% &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Mounted&lt;/span&gt; on
tmpfs                      &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2917628    1020   2916608   1&lt;/span&gt;% /dev
tmpfs                      &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2917628       0   2917628   0&lt;/span&gt;% /mnt
tmpfs                      &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2917628       0   2917628   0&lt;/span&gt;% /apex
/dev/block/mmcblk0p61      &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3096336 1637424   1442528  54&lt;/span&gt;% /
/dev/block/mmcblk0p62       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;806288  414160    375744  53&lt;/span&gt;% /vendor
tmpfs                      &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2917628    6432   2911196   1&lt;/span&gt;% /sbin
/dev/block/mmcblk0p48        &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;12016    7480      4212  64&lt;/span&gt;% /vendor/dsp
/dev/block/mmcblk0p60       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;237536     212    229464   1&lt;/span&gt;% /cache
/sbin/.&lt;span class=&quot;property&quot;&gt;magisk&lt;/span&gt;/block/data  &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;52885008 8501436  44236116  17&lt;/span&gt;% /sbin/.&lt;span class=&quot;property&quot;&gt;magisk&lt;/span&gt;/modules
/data/media               &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;52885008 8501436  44236116  17&lt;/span&gt;% /storage/emulated
whyred:/ $
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can guess by the size of the partition, the internal storage in my device is mounted on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/storage/emulated&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now just create a mount path in linux file system for this path. Open the Linux Deploy app on your phone, stop the container if its running. Go to the mount points settings and tap on the plus button on the top right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;100%&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/images/linux/Linux_Deploy_10.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Android path &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/storage/emulated&lt;/code&gt; goes in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/code&gt; field and the linux path goes in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Target&lt;/code&gt;. Tap on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OK&lt;/code&gt; and start the container again, login to the system and see if you can access the sdcard. You will probably see &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Permission Denied&lt;/code&gt; error when you try to access the folder, its because the user is not part of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aid_everybody&lt;/code&gt; groups you can check that by the command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ls -l
total &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;
drwx--x--x. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 21&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;00&lt;/span&gt; sdcard

$ groups android
android : android aid_graphics aid_sdcard_rw aid_inet 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can fix that by adding the linux user(android in my case) to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aid_everybody&lt;/code&gt; group. Use the command below to do this, you will have to logout and then login again to let this change take effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;splash&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo usermod -a -&lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;G&lt;/span&gt; aid_everybody android
$ exit
&lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Connection&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;192.168.0.137&lt;/span&gt; closed.

&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// Login again and check&lt;/span&gt;
$ cd sdcard
$ ls
&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
$ ls -l &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
total &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1623408&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Alarms&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;19 10&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;33&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;DCIM&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 13&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;26&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Documents&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;18 08&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;36&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/span&gt;
-rw-rw----. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;8589934592&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;24 19&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;57&lt;/span&gt; linux.&lt;span class=&quot;property&quot;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 13&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Movies&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Notifications&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;15 18&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Pictures&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Podcasts&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Ringtones&lt;/span&gt;
drwxrwx---. &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; root aid_everybody       &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;17 09&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;51&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Shows&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For external sdcard, just repeat these steps and use the correct mount points to access all the files on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that’s all folks, if you reached here you have a fully functional linux machine. This was a long process, but we are just getting started, there’s a lot more we can achieve with it. In the future posts I will be telling you how you can extend this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As an ad-block proxy server for your home network with Pi-Hole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A media server to stream your favorite movies and TV Shows with Plex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have more ideas in mind please let me know. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="hacking" /><category term="DIY" /><summary type="html">Phones have become very powerful these days. Its easy to find an Android phone under $200 that is capable of powering up a desktop computer with decent performance. I was thinking about setting up a media server in my home network so I can watch movies and TV shows on all devices, I was convinced to use a Raspberry Pie for this but then I thought what if I use my Android phone for the same, its much more capable than a pie and has a lot hardware capabilities that the pie doesn’t offer out of the box. So I set course and took out my old Android phone, did some hacking and got the media server working on it. Its a long process to setup the media server and the first step in getting their is to install Ubuntu or any other Linux distribution on the Android phone. I’ll talk about the media server setup some other day but lets see how to install Ubuntu on Android.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Social Media Distancing</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/social-media-distancing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Media Distancing" /><published>2020-02-10T18:03:25+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-10T18:03:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/social-media-distancing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/social-media-distancing">&lt;p&gt;I am obsessed with app notifications. I’ve been trying to get away from screens but I’m addicted to all of my devices. I’m always online and I never cut-off from internet. Even when I’m accompanied with people I enjoy talking to, I keep thinking about my phone. I was using my phone every where, at the coffee shop, at the restaurants, in office working hours and also in the washroom. I stopped going out on weekends and preferred to watch movies and shows at home on my laptop. I stayed awake late nights sacrificing 2-3 hrs of precious sleep for nothing but to watch some YouTube videos. I hurt my eyes every night because the dimmest brightness is still too bright in the dark. My devices started owning me. This over-possession of devices has reduced my engagement in concrete and meaningful discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the previous month I was at my friend’s place. In between all the fun, I felt my phone’s vibration. I tried being in the conversation but I couldn’t stop thinking about the notification. What could’ve changed in the world for which I am notified of? And my friends were able to figure out that I was in a different world. I felt bad and I knew that I missed the joy of “being” with my friends. I knew that I love talking to people but the phone was taking over and I couldn’t stop thinking about this loss. Being concerned about it and addressing it as a problem, introspecting, I concluded that its not an issue with notifications and devices, it’s an issue with self control, that’s how people get addicted to things. This addiction was bad and something had to do be done and I’m glad that I realized that–and not too late!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inputs&quot;&gt;Inputs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-cleanup&quot;&gt;The Cleanup&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did was to minimise the number of notifications I get on my phone. Though there is a way to disable notifications completely, I don’t think it’s a suitable option for me as I can’t afford losing some important notifications which really need my attention. What worked well for me was to uninstall tons of apps which I rarely use and disable notifications for apps which are not so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;limited-app-usage&quot;&gt;Limited App Usage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All modern operating systems have a really good feature to limit app usage. I set a limit to the apps which were taking most of my time, but it couldn’t work well for me as I found myself discarding warnings shown by the OS for limited usage. Instead, I chose a more restrictive approach I uninstalled the apps which can be accessed from a computer. It not only removed the notifications altogether but also helped me save a lot of time as it significantly dropped the number of times I opened them in a day. Some of the apps which fall in this category: Twitter, YouTube, Reddit, Quora, Instagram. I personally started seeing pretty good results with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;better-sleep-cycles&quot;&gt;Better sleep cycles&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows that getting 7-8 hrs sleep every night has great health benefits but are we really getting it? I wasn’t. So, as part of this process I also wanted to improve my sleeping cycles. To achieve that I stopped using all gadgets 45 minutes before bedtime and enabled Do not Disturb to silent each and every notification after 10:00PM, no Slack, no Gmail, no Whatsapp and no Reddit. I borrowed this idea from this amazing podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=De9pbbb_4VE&amp;amp;t=559s&quot;&gt;FREE OF COST Fitness Consultation - Luke Coutinho on The Ranveer Show&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-discipline-and-the-will&quot;&gt;The Discipline and the Will&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously an ambitious path to follow. Initially, it was hard to get away from the phone and for some days I couldn’t follow the plan at all because without the phone I felt I had nothing to do, I was bored. Even if I was not using my Social Media I was thinking about it all the time. Like every fight against addiction, this too did take a lot of discipline and a sheer will to make it work. Forming a habit is hard and a forming a good one even harder. Again, I borrowed ideas from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits - James Clear&lt;/a&gt; to get rid of bad habits and form the good ones. I challenged myself to follow it for month and tracked progress on a chart, marked mistakes on the calendar. Looking at the calendar motivates me to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outputs&quot;&gt;Outputs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting off from the internet and social media significantly improved my life. Individually, these changes look tiny but combined these are monumental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-time&quot;&gt;More time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might not be visible but when quantified, the amount of time I spent on the internet browsing garbage turned out to be huge, keep aside the time taken in context-switching! Now that I have bandwidth available I can utilise it for constructive use-cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;improved-focus--attention-spans&quot;&gt;Improved focus &amp;amp; attention spans&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was easily distracted by notifications. Now that they are gone, I started seeing improvements in focus on my work and tasks at hand. Most of the times I am focussed like a Hawk. My attention spans are getting longer and I don’t get bored easily now its totally on the person I am talking to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;faster-reading-speed---my-new-super-power&quot;&gt;Faster reading speed - my new super power&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more time at hand, I started reading a lot. My reading speed has improved and I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0062301233/ref=x_gr_w_bb_sin?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=x_gr_w_bb_in-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=3626&amp;amp;creative=24790&quot;&gt;Elon Musk’s Biography&lt;/a&gt; in 8-days. I am about to read more books in a year than I read in my entire life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;yoga-gave-me-the-fittest-body&quot;&gt;Yoga gave me the fittest body&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know me personally, you know that I have never put a step in a gym not because I am fit but I am lazy and I make excuses. Now I am changed man, I started with an easy challenge of 30-pushups a day no matter what. That made my upper body stronger. Then, I have started doing Yoga. I can do a 240 seconds consistent headstand, tripod headstand with no wall support. My aim is to get fit and strong enough to do a handstand. I now have the fittest body of my lifetime and I am seeing consistent improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-sleep---dreams-are-back&quot;&gt;Deep sleep - Dreams are back!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thr trick of cutoff from gadgets before 45 minutes to bed worked well. Initially I couldn’t fall asleep on time, perhaps it was because my body and my mind weren’t habitual of going to bed early. One way to fix it was by force waking up early, even without completing 8 hrs of sleep, so the body gets tired by the end of the day. It started working out and I could fall asleep within 30 minutes. I never realised earlier that my dreams were gone, I did when started dreaming again perhaps getting in to the deep sleep was the reason. Deep sleep is highly underrated, your next day depends on it, your life depends on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I didn’t get these results just by avoiding my phone. I got these because I started doing things which made me hyper productive. I started talking to good people, my social groups changed and we discussed meaningful stuff. Seeing these great results for the next subsequent months I started doing more productive things. Just by putting a limit on social media and device usage I could do so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t write this to show how bad technology is. I love tech and knowing about it has always helped me grow faster in career. I’m just putting a limit on its usage and trying to think more of how beautiful life can be a few inches above that screen. Technology has a huge share of productive usecases in all imaginable situations but it also has negative implications. There has to be a limit on it’s usage and I’ve started creating mine. You should too. Try whatever works out for you, no one is perfect but there is always a scope improvement this reminds me of a mind blowing passage from the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/1250194466/ref=x_gr_w_bb_sin?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=x_gr_w_bb_in-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=3626&amp;amp;creative=24790&quot;&gt;Creative Selection - Ken Kocienda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Lombardi joined the Green Bay Packers in 1959, he made an immediate and indelible first impression. In front of a portable blackboard as the players sat down, he picked up a piece of chalk and began to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Gentlemen,” he said, “we have a great deal of ground to cover. We’re going to do things a lot differently than they’ve been done here before . . . [We’re] going to relentlessly chase perfection, knowing full well we will not catch it, because perfection is not attainable. But we are going to relentlessly chase it because, in the process, we will catch excellence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catching excellence, this is what I believe in and feel fortunate enough to know how to achieve it. I have no PHD in life advice, this is a write-up of what worked for me and how I got inspired. The content and links I shared in the post were life changing for me I highly recommend them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am obsessed with app notifications. I’ve been trying to get away from screens but I’m addicted to all of my devices. I’m always online and I never cut-off from internet. Even when I’m accompanied with people I enjoy talking to, I keep thinking about my phone. I was using my phone every where, at the coffee shop, at the restaurants, in office working hours and also in the washroom. I stopped going out on weekends and preferred to watch movies and shows at home on my laptop. I stayed awake late nights sacrificing 2-3 hrs of precious sleep for nothing but to watch some YouTube videos. I hurt my eyes every night because the dimmest brightness is still too bright in the dark. My devices started owning me. This over-possession of devices has reduced my engagement in concrete and meaningful discussions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootcamp Coach</title><link href="https://vinayjain.me/posts/ios-bootcamp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootcamp Coach" /><published>2019-09-18T06:39:25+05:30</published><updated>2019-09-18T06:39:25+05:30</updated><id>https://vinayjain.me/posts/iOS-bootcamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vinayjain.me/posts/ios-bootcamp">&lt;p&gt;When I was in college I used to teach school students Mathematics and Physics, which still are my favorite subjects. I also presented a few tech related topics in my college to help my friends understand them better. I enjoy teaching, it’s fun and it is always a good learning exercise for me as well. It gives an entirely different perspective to learning and being on the other side makes me feel more confident of the things I already know. But after I graduated and started working in the software industry I didn’t get enough opportunities and couldn’t find time to do it. I attended tech meetups and thought of presenting a few topics but couldn’t, for me preparing a presentation was a herculean task that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;opportunity-and-time&quot;&gt;Opportunity and Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am working with Gojek right now and they organize a 3 months bootcamp for the new joiners(fresh graduates) to pick up the pace. The participants must enrol for all the courses in the bootcamp. These 3 months are divided into Core Engineering, DevOps, Data Engineering, Mobile Development and other tech stuff, you can read more about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gojekengineering.com/what-is-the-go-jek-engineering-bootcamp-de7778836da9&quot;&gt;Gojek Engineering Bootcamp here&lt;/a&gt;. Since I am an iOS developer, the organisers asked me if I was interested in coaching the iOS bootcamp. Coaching the bootcamp means I will be out of the office for a week and doing so will affect the timelines of deliverables I already have. I was interested in taking this opportunity but first, it had to be approved by the manager. My manager is a great guy, I knew he won’t disappoint me, 2-3 meetings and little rescheduling helped us figure out ways through which I would make it to the bootcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ios-bootcamp&quot;&gt;iOS Bootcamp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iOS bootcamp was short and so was Android, no offence intended and none taken. One week is a very short period to teach iOS to people who have never done it before. You have to teach them the language, tell them about the ecosystem, the development environment and also about UI components. One good thing about teaching iOS in 2019 is that you don’t have to teach Objective-C, which actually is a great language but teaching it in a bootcamp will probably take more efforts and a lot more time, Swift on the other hand can be taught easily. So we planned to teach the basics of Swift. Also, to let the bootcampers get the feel of iOS and mobile development in general, we decided to build a TicTacToe game within the bootcamp timeline. Building the game kept the bootcampers engaged and interested in learning iOS, it also helped us cover important topics like building user interfaces with the Cocoa Touch, unit tests and concurrency etc. Other important topics like data persistence, animations, audio support were given as part of coding assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the final two assignments, we had split the bootcampers into teams, each team had 4 members. The last two days we didn’t teach them much, we gave them assignments, solved open issues, review code and let them present what they had built in front of everyone. Some of the teams made apps that were so good that with a little polish they can be uploaded to the App Store. I personally liked the last two days, seeing their progress made us feel proud of ourselves and implicitly gave us feedback that we did well. The last session of last was all about this, one on ones with the bootcampers, feedback for them, feedback for us and a few fun activities. We received some negative feedbacks as well but they were just for the initial days where the participants felt that the theory was boring and they needed more hands-on exercises. Overall, I enjoyed the bootcamp. The next bootcamp will be in Jakarta and if given a chance I would definitely enrol again and fix the mistakes and use the learnings in my first bootcamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you reached here, thanks for your time. Also, if you are interested in working with Gojek please shoot me an email or maybe head to the careers page to see the current openings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ios" /><summary type="html">When I was in college I used to teach school students Mathematics and Physics, which still are my favorite subjects. I also presented a few tech related topics in my college to help my friends understand them better. I enjoy teaching, it’s fun and it is always a good learning exercise for me as well. It gives an entirely different perspective to learning and being on the other side makes me feel more confident of the things I already know. But after I graduated and started working in the software industry I didn’t get enough opportunities and couldn’t find time to do it. I attended tech meetups and thought of presenting a few topics but couldn’t, for me preparing a presentation was a herculean task that time.</summary></entry></feed>